this is such an amazing problem we are
given this right triangle whose length
of this part of the hypotenuse is five
and we have a circle inscribed in it
whose radius is 2 units we have been
asked to find the area of this shaded
region that is this blue region can you
solve it what do you think in how many
ways can this question be solved I'd
love to hear your thoughts in the
comments okay so first thing first since
this side of the triangle is tangent to
to this circle so this radius will be
perpendicular to this side so this will
be
90° now draw this radius it will also be
perpendicular to this side of the
triangle as it is also tangent to this
circle so it will be of length two and
this will be
90° look at this quadrilateral all four
sides are 90° and both of them are of
length two so it will be a square of
side length two thus both of them will
also be two great now here comes the
magic we will use the two tangent
theorem which states that the lengths of
two tangents drawn from the same
external point to a circle are equal now
this is a tangent and this is also a
tangent to this circle and they are
drawn from the same external point this
one so both of them will be equal
therefore this will also become five
same goes for these tangents both of
them will be equal let us label them as
X excellent now consider this right
triangle this side is of length x + 2
this is of length 2 + 5 or 7 and the
hypotenuse is x + 5 so we will use the
Pythagoras Theorem to find X we get x +
5² = x + 2 2 + 7 s this gives x 2 + 5 2
or 25 + 2 * x * 5 or 10 x = x 2 + 2 2 or
4 + 2 * x * 2 or 4 x + 49 this x² will
get cancelled out and we are left with
this 25 + 10 x = 4 + 4 x + 49 or 4x + 53
take 4X on left side and 25 on right
side to get 6 x = 28 or x = 28 / 6 which
can be simplified to 14 over 3 so far so
good thus this side length will be x + 2
or 14 by 3 plus this 2 can be written as
6 by 3 so it becomes 20
by3 now the area of this shaded region
will be same as the area of this
triangle minus the area of this circle
the area of this triangle will be 20x 3
* 7 / 2 or 140 / 6 which when simplified
becomes 70 by 3 and the area of this
circle will be Pi r^ 2ar or < * 2^ 2 or
4 piun so the area of this shaded region
will be 70 by 3 - 4 Pi cool were you
able to solve it what approach did you
use use to solve this question let me
know in the comments so good